Guide to the Adelia Gates Hensley collection, Circa 1871-1951 MVC0008.MS
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Adelia Gates Hensley collection
circa 1871-1951
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0008.MS
6.25 Linear Feet 1 slim document box, 6 flat boxes
Adelia Gates Hensley was the second president of Mount Vernon Seminary, founded in Washington, D.C. in 1875. Mount Vernon Seminary and College merged with The George Washington University in 1999. This collection contains correspondence, photographs, silverware, a diploma, and mortorboard of and belonging to Adelia Gates Hensley, president of Mount Vernon Seminary from 1915 to 1923.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: Photographs and prints, Speeches and correspondence, and Memorabilia.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains photographs, prints, correspondence, silverware, a diploma, and a mortarboard of and belonging to Adelia Gates Hensley. The materials range in date from circa 1870 to 1951.
Biographical / Historical
Adelia Gates Hensley graduated from Mount Holyoke College in 1877. She joined the faculty of Mount Vernon Seminary in 1884 and taught history, literature, and art history. She later succeeded Elizabeth Somers as President of Mount Vernon Seminary from 1915 to 1923.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. Collection transferred to Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Women's colleges; Women -- Education; Hensley, Adelia Gates; Mount Vernon Seminary
- Photographs and prints, 1908-1951; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains photographs and prints of Adelia Gates Hensley, including one of her husband James Hensley.
  - Small photo of Adelia Gates Hensley, 1908-1909; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adelia Gates Hensley with President of Mt. Holyoke college and accompanying letter, 1917; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Print of watercolor of Adelia Gates Hensley, 1951; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "In the early years of M.V.S. and our Mrs. Hensley", undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Little Adelia Gates at Seven, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mounted sepia photograph of Adelia Gates Hensley, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Paper print of photographs taken in 1884-1885, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - James Hensley with accompanying letter, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sepia photograph of older Adelia Gates Hensley, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Small photograph of young Adelia Gates Hensley, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Small photograph of young Adelia Gates Hensley, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Sepia print of watercolor painting of Adelia Gates Hensley, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Glass plate photograph of "Miss Gates The Student at Mt. Holyoke", undated; Series 1 (Box 2)
- Correspondence and speeches, 1916-1929; Series 2
  This series contains correspondence to and from Adelia Gates Hensley as well as speeches written by her.
  - Correspondence and speeches written by Adelia Gates Hensley, 1916-1919; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence concerning Adelia Gates Hensley's death and the settling of her estate, 1923-1929; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Memorabilia, circa 1871-1917; Series 3
  This series includes sterling silver holloware and flatware as well as a framed diploma and mortar board from the personal collection of Adelia Gates Hensley, president of Mount Vernon Seminary from 1915 to 1923.
  - Silver plate serving cup with Adelia Gates Hensley's "H" monogram, circa 1871-1879; Series 3 (Box 6, Item 1)
    Made by Wallace Brothers' Silver Company in Wallingford, CT. Pattern #V456. Likely made from a nickel alloy known as German silver. The company retained the name "Wallace Brothers Silver Company" only from 1871-1879, thus this piece is dated within those years.
  - Silver plate creamer with Adelia Gates Hensley's "H" monogram, circa 1871-1879; Series 3 (Box 6, Item 2)
  - Silver plate coffee pot with Adelia Gates Hensley's "H" monogram, circa 1871-1879; Series 3 (Box 6, Item 3)
    Made by Wallace Brothers Silver Company in Wallingford, CT. Pattern #V456. Likely made from a nickel alloy known as German silver. The company retained the name "Wallace Brothers Silver Company" only from 1871-1879, thus this piece is dated within those years.
  - 3 sterling silver coffee spoons with "H" monogram, 1891; Series 3 (Box 7, Item 1)
    The lion and "W" in a circle on the handle indicate that these spoons were designed by the Whiting Manufacturing Company, formed in 1866 and bought by Gorham in 1924.
    This pattern is called Louis XV and was patented in 1891.
    One of the spoons is also stamped with "Galt & Bro." indicating that Galt & Bros., a company established in 1802 based in Washington, D.C. bought the forks from Whiting.
    see: http://www.925-1000.com/patterns_Whiting_4.html
  - 5 sterling silver soup spoons with "H" monogram, circa 1892-1923; Series 3 (Box 7, Item 2)
    The back of the handles are stamped with the word "sterling", "925/1000" and an unidentified symbol. 925/1000 identifies it as sterling silver because sterling silver legally must contain 92.5% pure silver. The remaining 7.5% is another metal, usually copper.
    The inscription "Galt & Bro." on the back of the handle indicates that the spoons were either produced or sold by Galt & Bros., a company established in 1802 based in Washington, D.C. The fleur de lis was a hallmark of James Galt's former company, Davis & Galt.
    The spoons are dated between ca. 1892 and 1923 because the company changed its name from M.W. Galt & Bro & Co to Galt & Bro in 1892 and Adelia Gates Hensley died in 1923.
  - Sterling silver serving spoon with "H" monogram, 1910; Series 3 (Box 7, Item 3)
    The hallmark "Alvin Sterling" on the handle indicates that this spoon was manufactured by the Alvin Corporation, founded in 1886.
    The pattern of this spoon is called Maryland and was patented in 1910.
    see: http://www.sterlingflatwarefashions.com/CatalogPgs/Alvin/Maryld.html
  - Sterling silver flat, pointed spoon with "ADH" monogram, circa 1912-1914; Series 3 (Box 7, Item 4)
    The hallmark on this piece (an "A" in the form of a hammer with the handle extending through the word "Stone" and crossing the "t")indicates that it was manufactured by Arthur Stone and his workshop. Stone's private company was in business in Massachusetts from 1901-1937.
    The W stamp on each spoon indicates that it was manufactured specifically by Alfred Wickstrom, a member of Stone's workshop, between ca. 1912-1914.
    see: http://www.925-1000.com/a_stone.html
  - Adelia Gates Hensley's diploma from Mount Holyoke, 1917; Series 3 (Box 4)
  - Adelia Gates Hensley's mortarboard, undated; Series 3 (Box 5)